this is a magicaya 19. two types of
thinking and
and
it has a parallel in the Chinese
arguments which is 102
and I've kind of tried to just join them
together so and I'll let you know
so and I'll let you know
when the argument argument says
something a bit different
it's not much difference but
so on one occasion the blessing this one
said this because before my
Enlightenment while I was still seeking
Enlightenment it occurred to me
suppose I divide my thinking into two
classes then I sit on one side thinking
pertaining to sensuality
aversion and cruelty and I said on the
other side thinking pertaining to
non-centrality or renunciation
non-irable and non-cruelty
essential as I lived
and the argument says in solitude
Pali continues diligent persistent
vigilant a sensual averse or cruel thought arose
a sensual averse or cruel thought arose
in me
and I understood it
like this
this class of thinking leads to my own
affliction to the other others Affliction and to
to the other others Affliction and to
the Affliction on both
it obstructs wisdom sides with
difficulties and needs away from Nirvana
when I considered this that type of
thinking subsided in me whenever
essential aversive or cruel thinking
arose in me I abandoned it tamed it and
brought it to an end I an argument says
I do not accept it I vomited it up
because I saw that countless evil and
wholesome States would certainly arise
because of such thoughts so I think I've
stopped there
well we covered this before
but I guess we can repeat
because it says that when the thought of
sensuality arose in him
what did he do
did he watch moment-to-moment experience
did he focus on Sensations concentrate
on nostrils
did he do any of that
no
he recognized them for what they are and
he didn't just stay mindful but he then
established the context
of the pedal the danger the lack of
satisfaction the Trap while those
thoughts were present
so he developed the context while the
thoughts are present
then the context neutralizes them and
they subside they leave you they go away
you don't get rid of them or you don't
stop your mind from thinking indirectly
because that's another way of grasping
onto debate
so the emphasis is on the context
and that's how you were vomit it out for
sure
so you can't just like okay
like okay
oh this is bad this is bad but I think
you have to do it yeah but what I mean
is that like you could easily
think like I just you might not actually
like I just you might not actually
understand that that's bad
but you just sort of say to yourself oh
this is bad or this is a problematic
this is harmful but you're actually just
not seeing any problem with it and just
kind of trying to do
but but it's more about actually trying
to understand why you want to see that
it's very Advent as the Body Center you
know Buddha is both he already sees this
leads away from Ivana he's not
you know he knows what your mind is he
knows what it isn't so this obstructs
wisdom so he already knows why it is bad
but let's say somebody who is trying to
do this practice there's obviously not
abolish either they can still do it
if they recognize that that first and
foremost thing is like yes thoughts
arise on their own mind thinks on its
own eyes want to cease objects is one to
hear sounds mind will think thoughts
so the reason why these thoughts are
coming is because you have not
understood the context of the danger and
you have not understood the context of
the danger because you either lack
restraint well slightly straight or on
top of that also
your views are on the level of uh just
accepting Central thoughts or getting
rid of them either way you're acting out
the discomfort of the pressure that
those thoughts put on you so
so
precepts have to come first sense
restraint guarding of the sense doors
watchfulness of your intentions as we
repeat so many times
and then when these thoughts arise you
see them without immediately impulsively
already being down the rabbit hole of
acting out of them
and once they be completed on the basis
of your restraint and and kind of
that aggregate The Virtue that has been
developed beforehand you think okay they
are a problem these thoughts are a
problem in the sense of abate is a
problem because I still don't quite know
how to not get caught that's the problem
the fact is Mara will put a bait in his
in what he controls because it's his
but for as long as you think none of
these thoughts are the problem I must
get rid of these thoughts you basically
are holding the view that Mara has no
right to bait you he has no right to set
the trap for you
and that means oh you're already caught
you're already in the Trap you're
already taking what doesn't belong to
you
so the practice of virtue and the Somali
that comes out of it
that's what enables you to have the
pressuring thought without acting out
without automatically losing perspective
and then you can start this practice
okay this pressure is it Pleasant or
unpleasant it's unpleasant is it for my
welfare like would something set up as a
trap be for anyone's welfare if
something is generally good would you
need to track people into it
so you start reflecting like that and
these thoughts will subside
because you're not anymore providing
that ignorant basis that they require
same goes for your will same goes for
cruelty so what would you say that
so what would you say that
you think so that thinking on that
thought sort of following it on that
that is a choice oh yeah definitely
definitely sure yeah that's exactly and
so when it says oh you abandon these
thoughts that's how you abandon them by
not choosing them and by actually still
emphasizing through your mindfulness and
right through collectiveness the context
of no it's dangerous
any woman with the Trap is dangerous yes
it's unpleasant for it to be here and
pressure me but not as unpleasant as
being hooked by it and then dragged for
days and then had to redo everything
from the start
so it's unpleasant only because you're
still not sure whether you'll be able to
restrain yourself but the only way to
become sure is to start restraining
yourself and it is a choice it's always
a choice every single time
when whenever has anyone in the history
of samsara acted out of ill will or
sensuality it was a choice on the level
of their thought
yeah but I'll do something every it
cannot be otherwise that's the whole
point even being able to see that
that I have a choice here that's already
quite well that's what I'm saying like
you you won't start yeah you won't start
to practice by seeing that choice
for that you need to start seeing your
mind and for that you need to be
established in Virtual and get it right
to you we said that before when the
students talk about the
um unenlightened bodhisatta it actually
means not completely enlightened body
starts it doesn't mean Enlighten put too
General doesn't know what he's doing
just roams around the world trying to
figure it out no means you already has a
pretty good knowledge what enlightenment
is he just hasn't still fully developed
it that's even in here it's indicated
because he already knows what would lead
to nibana and what wouldn't lead to
nibana means he already has the right
View so any practices that unenlightened
so any practices that unenlightened
bodhisatta does basically means well at
least you have to have a right view for
even those practices to apply to you
and for that right view you need to be
established in virtue
and uh again and that's on the level of
choice every single time
right choice her the wrong choice
but even though it is still kind of
interesting in that
in the suit he even he starts he doesn't
start by just directly saying oh this
thought arose I just abandon this yeah
he's test he starts by reflecting on the
nature of that thought and then through
saying okay this is dangerous this is
perilous and then you know whenever the
thought arises because he sees he does
not need to keep on like reflecting
about it he's able to abundance yeah the
reason why people would immediately jump
onto a thought I had to accept it or
deny it or cancel it is because they
don't see their mind so they're fully
identified with that with my days so
this reaction is just the result of
their identification so in order to
start actually seeing the difference
there you need to stop acting out as we
say so many times you have to endure it
you have to endure that pressure and not
act out not break precepts and not try
to get rid of it because it's unpleasant
it's not right
and and the simile it was included in
that is the summary of The Cow herd
curbing the cows his cows so just as in
the last month of the rainy season in
the Autumn when the crops thickened a
Cowherd would guard his cows by
constantly tapping and poking them on
this side in that with a stick to check
and curb them why is that because he
sees that he could be beaten imprisoned
fined or blamed if you let them straight
into others crops
so too I saw in unwholesome States
danger degradation and defilement and in
wholesome States the blessing purity of
non-sensuality or pronunciation
what do the cows stand for in this
simile tonight is that
tonight is that
so you don't let the mind wander into
the presented pastures of sensuality or
real will or cruelty you keep an eye on
your mind
so I shall not abandon
the context of danger the power of the
Trap because if I do means cows are
already grazing in someone else's field
they're already taking what doesn't
belong to me but I am paired with those
cows people see them as mine I can say
there's nothing's real in reality and
these cows don't exist but
well that won't stop people from beating
me if my cows eat in their fields so it
doesn't matter what My Views are
practically letting my cows graze in what doesn't
letting my cows graze in what doesn't
belong to me will lead to mine yeah I'm
gonna feel I'm going to pay the price
for it so
so it will be very unwise to ignore that
situation so he keeps an eye on his cows
so he practices the the the sense
restraint the context
clarifies as it protects it so that the
cows don't
um stray into the fields on account of
him lapsing and forgetting what's
important and getting distracted by I
don't know side sounds smell taste
touches around the field what he is
and there's the Curbing and the Cowherd
the curbing is that thinking that choice
the choices yeah it's the choice yeah I
can I can choose to ignore this
which is right in front of me
or I can choose to know I will think
about the context so that the cows stay
in on this side of the fence and they
don't go over there yeah how long they
have to do it well it doesn't matter if
I have to do it for the rest of my life
I'll do it because again if they go into
other people's fields that will be my
punishment but then as the simile continues later
but then as the simile continues later
on you know other crops will die out you
won't always be there to the same extent
so there will be time where you can
relax but not where where the
Temptations and pressures are right
there yeah even if there's an unwholesome
yeah even if there's an unwholesome
State there isn't like ill will or
craving you're still thinking about the
possibility but you're still fighting on
um yeah which possible the possibility
of ill will or quoting Horizon yeah sure
well that's the possibility I mean it's
like yes okay they're not eating in
other people's crops now but
the crops the sensuality the the people
that annoy me are still around me
and if I lose the context of that
uh my mind will jump and leap at the
opportunity so I must emphasize the protecting of my
so I must emphasize the protecting of my
mind not figuring out or fixing the
world or the crops around me that tempt
me that's an endless task
you know there's a thought of
pronunciation but that thought is
it's not something that you sort of
like start fabricating no exactly mainly
it's it's within the same context right
that sensuality
when the when the sensuality is pressing
your real will choosing to not go down
that and accept that date that's the
thought to enunciation it's not the
third thing you do upon that yeah
understanding that that sensuality yeah
that direction is
developing that
non-sensuality yeah that dispassion for
essential energy yeah there was a note
in the
in that suit in the back of this
translation and it said
e i
thoughts of love and kindness and and
also but that seems very unlikely it's
completely you can ignore all the notes at the back
you can ignore all the notes at the back
of my journals it's all from the
commenters it has absolutely no
connection with the actual down except
on paper yeah no it's it's always that
and you could see where all these
contemporary worldly views stem from it's exactly I
worldly views stem from it's exactly I
don't know see it's too subtle well
again person who is not developed in virtue
person who is not developed in virtue
who would who would have not lived in
seclusion sense restraint guarding the
sense those
watchful of their intentions being white
for will not see their mind if they
don't see their mind they will not
recognize the whole domain of the middle
ground between sensuality actively
thinking sensual thoughts and not
choosing that while those thoughts are
present they will not see their choice
it will not it could not be comparent so
then the only way they could make sense
out of this instruction would be okay so
I must think the opposite and they
wouldn't understand that that's going
too far the other way now because you
will think the opposite with your
sensuality it's because sincerity is
here as your context you're thinking the
loving kindness thoughts or asuba asuba
any discussed to to get rid of it
because you're already decrypt by
sensuality because you already don't see
the danger the pedal because the whole
domain of developing the context it just
doesn't exist in that person
and the word is actually I remember when
I first saw that in Pali I was like oh
that makes so much more sense
how can you practice love and kindness
when you're angry
well according to the commentaries
that's that's the best time to practice
Yeah
so it is a kind of quite
important to
like actually means it's not that
obvious what constitutes a thought of
sensuality basically or intention of
sensuality so that's already something
like you can't just kind of start this
practice taking for granted you're why
wouldn't it be obvious to somebody
why would that still be unclear to a
person is there well they're habitually
acting out yes they're not upset in the
body yeah so when you start restraining
then it becomes more then you can
experience your speech and then it will
become obvious what these thoughts are
yeah yeah
yeah
but even then like yeah because and
restraint then also needs to be then
understood as and restraining intentions
of yeah
so it's yeah yeah
okay so this is a continues because
whatever Baker frequently thinks would
be Tuckers and partners upon the charas
that will become the inclination of his
mind if he frequently thinks and Ponders upon
if he frequently thinks and Ponders upon
centrality he has abandoned the thoughts
of renunciation or non-sensuality to
cultivate the thought of sensual desire
and then his mind inclines to essential
thinking likewise with aversion
likewise with aversion
and cruelty he has abandoned
non-inversion and he has abandoned
non-cruelty and the argoma Chinese argoma adds a
and the argoma Chinese argoma adds a
monk who has not abandoned thoughts of
sensual sensuality of ill will and
cruelty will be unable to free himself
in birth old age disease
and suffering from tears and weeping
he will not be able to free himself from
Tuka
I remember it also said which I kind of
liked the combination it said whatever
among frequently or whatever person
frequently thinks and Ponders upon his
mind will Delight in that and then in
the in the party he says that will
become the inclination of his mind so [Music]
[Music]
I actually have a question about because
especially you know
you're quite secluded
um so it's very you know you are more
confronted with your thoughts which is
you know for this very pretty
good but then
you you can really start to
even in things that maybe not so
obviously Central it will still Delight
in your thinking because you know you're
you're by yourself and then you get your
threat and you
and you
you know it can be it can be agreeable
at least yeah and that's the choice
we're talking about
but then yeah it's sort of you can
choose to not
accept the applicability yeah
like yeah you find your mind thinking
those thoughts so as I said you can just
stop it because in a way you are not
doing it you're subjected to it but you
are then goading on the Mind carelessly
or showing it the danger
but to protect yeah you need to really
develop further on on standing Horseman
wholesome of course uh no you don't need
to develop the understanding of it in a
sense if you need to figure it out
you need to develop uh virtue in the
body and the speech
so not fuel it to unwholesome intentions
that you act out upon the level of the
body of speech
so
you know you'll be drawn from the course
things in the world but there are still
things that by body and by speech are
rooted in those same intentions and
every single time on a day-to-day basis
you choose to engage with them or not
every single time but most of the time
and that's why the the clarity between
truly what's Horsemen and wholesome is
still not seeing because you are still
polluting it with your actions so that's
like it would always be the uh the
advanced restrained by the precepts uh
it'll be secluded and so on but then
speech as well
don't just don't don't disappear like
mentally like a chit chat or pointless
debates and stuff like that it's great
with passion intention and ideas because
I give it I'm losing I'm losing the
self-awareness on account of doing this
and it's kind of also impulsive
you know that if if somebody if a man
decides to say something it's like a who
is that Sutra it will be said because
you say you have to kind of go against
it yes some a very difficult thing to to
know to do yeah so you recognize okay so
again you can't necessarily stop that
impulse overnight but you could
certainly stop like you know directing
it away from just careless pointless
meaningless uh that's why often even
like those eight practice precepts would
would sometimes be uh changed and uh and
include those uh like ways of right
speech like the gossip the Chit Chat uh the the
like the gossip the Chit Chat uh the the
slander and you abstain from all of that
as a practice not as some sort of
religious observance
um and that's how you would clarify that
and then even if you don't make the
effort to figure out wholesome it's
wholesome and wholesome you will because
you stop polluting it
so as I lived in solitude diligence
persistent indigenous thinking
pertaining to non-sensuality
non-aversion or non-cruelty arose in me
I understood thus this thinking
pertaining to non-sentuity non-inversion
non-cruelty has arisen in me this does
not lead to my own Affliction or to the
Affliction of others or to the fiction
of both it aids wisdom does not cause
difficulty and leads to nibana
if I think and contemplates these
thoughts even for a night even for a day
even for a night and day I see nothing
to fear from them
and the argument adds I rapidly
developed it made much of it if I
thought if a thought was uh with
non-sensuality of Rosemary I
intentionally kept on thinking it
and so I just kept on
and then back to the party but with
excessive thinking and contemplation on
my time my body when the body is tied
the Mind becomes Disturbed and when the
mind is Disturbed it is far from samadhi
composure and the argoma says says the same if I
and the argoma says says the same if I
have if I further had the thoughts if I
intentionally kept on thinking my body
will lose strength and my mind will be
troubled let me rather keep my mind in
check within continuously dwelling in in
a calm Unified
elevated having attained composure so
let my mind will not be troubled okay so
there's an important point there
the difference between the
certain implication in Bali and the set
implication in the other one that
describes it all the main things of the
agama says that he intentionally
developed and cultivated these thoughts
and kept on thinking is before he came
to the point of
um sort of realizing okay if I keep on
thinking this forever now so on the
basis of that Chinese part you can see
that that fatigue and tiredness comes on
a kind of intentional work of thinking
the right context not simply on account
of having thoughts all I had these
wholesome thoughts coming but these
thoughts basically presence of thoughts
means means fatigue so I must stop
thinking to calm myself down no no I must stop
to calm myself down no no I must stop
actively think these thoughts after I
have withdrawn them from sensuality they
are still there
they're still coming otherwise how would
I know they're still wholesome
so that's the tiring part the work
not the thoughts in themselves
and again you can only say I can rest
once you did the work not like oh well
that work is tiring thus I shall unify
my mind here and not even start with the
work what would be the criteria for
what would be the criteria for
Discerning
um
the the mind is
is what is is agitated on account of
Team lots of loss of composure no not
like agitated not like well you wouldn't
be going back to centrality but like it
would just not be calm the line would be
revolving around aspects of Dharma and
so on in the in a wholesome way but you
realize okay it's too much what for why
am I doing this I'm doing it to be well
I started doing it because I withdraw
myself from centrality to new will but I
am not going back to centrality near
well so I might as well stop doing this
for now
not stop thinking but stop intentionally
kind of fueling and revolving around
those wholesome thoughts stop the
intentional part of vitakovichara
not get rid of the guitar altogether
because that's the purpose it's not in
and of itself develop constant to Super
and constant disgust
no it's like some minds are more
frequently inclined towards sincerity
than others so
you keep losing the context you have to
make some effort when essentiality is
not present when you're not under the
pressure of enduring it uh yeah
cultivate the the ugly the the repulsive
and all of that so the then context will
be there waiting when sincerely comes
non-sensuality none ill will non-cruelty
those thoughts aspects of Dharma Clarity
of the presence of the phenomena and so
on thinking that intentionally
fortifies the context
but you realize okay but I am constantly
thinking so why don't I calm down why don't I
so why don't I calm down why don't I
stop the intentional
picking up with these thoughts
and that's why it's actually first genre
this what aguma describes is the first
genre when thinking and pondering has
been thoroughly withdrawn from wandering
back into five hindrances sensuality ill
will cruelty and then you recognize that
it's quite secluded now there are no
more concerns
Joys worries in regard to the world all
you have is thinking and pondering of a
very clear nature that you have actively
developed in regard to a wholesome States we drew
in regard to a wholesome States we drew
it from purified from and you realize oh
so I can stop doing this now
and when you stop doing it that's that
pleasure bone of seclusion from
unwholesome states that was developed
beforehand
how this child did polish with this
described China as well
the cows are safe you know the whole
situation is safe no more Temptations
have we drew them onto the field that's
not surrounded by other people's crops
and so on
I trained them they never wander away
they go a bit they come back I will
allow them I will bring them I would
allow them I would bring them I would
allow them I would bring them now allow
them and unless they come back on their
own I don't need to go and bring them I
don't need to allow them they won't go
anywhere let me just sit and rest well
thoughts and pondering is here around me
surrounding me and that's exactly what
the first genre is
let's see the work the pleasure of the
address comes after you did the work
not how again the whole commentary in in
today's practice expects it to be well
I'm I'm deeply immersed in sensuality
I'm gonna find a direct pathway access
to a meditation technique to some
pleasure of a different kind and that's
why I will forsake all of this that's
another Central pleasure
so I studied my mind internally settled
it brought to singularism composure
so that my mind would not be disturbed
and that's what
we would say is the
first genre basically
and the simile is of the Cowherd resting
while watching The Cows as you can as
you've said
um
he just he uh he just has to be mindful
that the cows are there so too there was
need need for me only to be mindful that
those states were there
persistence diligence was manifested in
me and recollection was not forgotten my
body was calm and unagitated my mind
settled and elevated
and then the argoma goes into
description of second genre third genre
of John after that yeah
where's the party goes into just the
standard first second third fourth
so so in that sense you would say that
quite contrary to believe that China is
invested in more like in intentional
um instead of waiting for it the
development of withdrawal from a
wholesome State yeah it's the
development it's not it's not a magical
kind of thing that would happen a kind
of disobservance of that observance
that's right the mark trains himself
thus he abandons this state he arouses
diligence to not to tolerate their
reason thoughts of sensuality but
actually work on the context of danger
in regard to them how do you tolerate
thoughts of centrality by the way you
can tolerate filters in shortly by
actively accepting them delighting them
thinking them
fantasizing them further acting out of
them but you can also tolerate the
thoughts of sensuality by
knowing that you should think about a
pedal the danger the bait the Trap the
depth the the chopping block all the
similes are good again but I'm too tired
to think about
nowadays now I'll think about it
tomorrow that's how I tolerate it that's
why diligence is not there
but then equally
you are tolerating them or tolerating
what sensuality brings on to you
by trying to get rid of it
when these thoughts are present you
don't want to think of the context while
they are harassing you you just want
them to stop harassing you so I just
think of soup I'll just think the
opposite that's how you get rid of this
that's how you overcome the engine
system not even close
so the work is on sustaining the context
invest in the work on the on that mental
level uh without any single exception
uh without any single exception
so that doesn't mean you have to do it
all the time that means that whenever
the sensuality is pressuring you you
have to do it the danger see what it is
the danger the Peril again you might
feel like I'll do this to get rid of the
pressure well no I'll do this for the
circle for its own sake for the sake of
developing the context
doesn't matter how long I'm I'm under
this pressure that's just an extra thing
that's trying to distract me from my
work trying to get and since there's things
trying to get and since there's things
coming around every day the subversion
is Centro ATM might as well get to know
you know get to know his nature well
yeah but see the problem with that
statement is oh I get to know it I'll
I'll investigate it I'll I'll come
closer to it I'll I'll induce it I'll
psychologize it no you don't have to
know it you don't have to pay attention
to it but you need to sustain the
recollection of the danger that if you
touch it
you're inflicting the eons of pain upon
you that's it
if you touch it if you accept it if you
if you reach for it it doesn't matter
whether it's to accept it or get rid of
it if you put your hand there
you're trapped that's it mother doesn't
care if you resist or not as long as you
affirm it
and that's the point
this is the same as the purifying of the
thoughts that we spoke the other day
exactly yeah yeah it's exactly that yeah
and it's it's like as the suitors say so
much it's whatever brings wholesome
states to arise and develop whatever
causes and increases the abandoning of
the unwholesome so it's like you need to
be able to see that what causes
wholesome states to arise and increase
what causes unwholesome states to to
diminish and you would see that if you
see your intentions exactly if you're
intention is still just trying to get
rid of things
that bother you internally it doesn't
matter what you're trying to figure out
you're doing it for wrong reasons you're
acting out
and that's why it won't work but like
and that's the thing like once you if if
you can see your intentions clearly then
it's not difficult to decide or to kind
of you don't need to kind of it's not
it's not such a big deal to figure out
okay what must I think about what must I
do it's it's really just quite simply
like what things but it is very clear
what what must do
um keep the precepts God the sense those
watch your mouth in terms of don't
engaging careless pointless the
ridiculous distracting speech that that
results in like again having to then
redo and recompose everything else watch
your intentions gather sense those be
secluded as much as you can those are
factual things you can do
this is a I thought I'd bring this up as
well because basically the noble
Eightfold Path and the second pointing
that is so from Right View then it's
right
and summer sunkappa
I'll just uh just read this section when
you understand wrong
as wrong sankapa and right Sankara is
right but that's your right view so
Santa is like
the party together making
determined uh creating
and it's translated as intention of
thought usually so it's the right
thought but it's the right
inclination provides attitude or direction of your
provides attitude or direction of your
thinking
[Music]
so that is your life you've seen what is
the right way of thinking the wrong way
of thinking
and what is the wrong song
yeah so
I'm just trying to
formulate a question for people using
the similar the cows so
the the Right View
see the point is like it's not just to
figure out what's right intention and
what's wrong intention to study it then
like you know get the etymology of the
world and now I have the right view
because I got all the information
it's to to see the relationship that
we've been describing for 45 minutes now
yeah of the right
of the thoughts right or wrong thoughts
and the mind
to see that Direct
link between the pastures and the cows
and your responsibility in it
because now you are the cause you you
you don't even see the character you're
completely identified so you see the
passages you go or you want to get rid
of it or whatever but you don't see the
weight this affects the mind no matter
what I what views I have what I hold why
whatever actually this is present mind
goes their way and this pleasure mine
goes that way understanding that
understanding the weight of that the
parallel of that the escape from that is
the Right View
it's basically understanding the root of
suffering and the way out of it because
that's where the suffering is
and that's exactly what samasankapa is
ah okay so again
whatever I might think about the
pastures and the bait and the cows
doesn't matter
what matters is that when this types of
thoughts are present this is how cows
behave is that to my for my benefit no is that
is that to my for my benefit no is that
for my welfare no is that from I am
burdening no
and then the opposite when these
thoughts are present this is how cows
don't behave and this is what they don't
do and that is for my welfare that is
for them even if I just want to stay a
householder it's still actually better for me if the
it's still actually better for me if the
Mind obeys me if my own mind is in my
control factually nobody can dispute
that and you recognize exactly what brings
and you recognize exactly what brings
that control or what decreases it and
that's that's why then the one with the
Right View would understand what the
right training of the mind is whether he
engages in it or not that's a separate
thing but he would at least know exactly
where where it boils down to
so that's yeah right view leads to this
recognition of right sankova
yeah so what is wrong some couple is
thoughts of sensuality aversion improves
it and that's why it's wrong it's not
because it's written on the sky that these
it's written on the sky that these
things are evil it's wrong because the
mind always
reacts in this way which always results
in again more burden more hassle more
distraction more Peril more depth more
payments later always no exceptions
let's look on on every level like from
the most mundane to the most to the
highest right it goes you can see it at
a basic level but it pertains to yeah
all the way through all the way through
and you have to ignore this this image
the the thought of there being two types
of thought that that is
um that
is
is pointing in in the direction of of
seeing wholesome and unhausen yeah
as the body side they said I would I
would say I would divide them into two
categories so you're already cease to be concerned
so you're already cease to be concerned
with every particular thought the
content of the content exactly I'd say
this well but this one's slightly
different it doesn't matter
doesn't partake in sincerity yes that's
the basket
everything else is irrelevant it's
particular it is
in your will yes that's the basket you
put it in that's it
so you gotta learn and make the effort
to keep emphasizing that the general
nature that this thought but takes in
and not be already pulled by the content
because see that's already being tracked
being fully absorbed in the content of
your thoughts and ignoring the fact that
the nature of a central thought is still
the same sensuality well like yeah you
have a lot of work to do then and again
you would be ignoring that if you're not
developed in the body and certainly not
developing speech
not restrained enough
if you are then then it becomes apparent
you are you are forcing yourself away
from being too too kind of engaged with
the automatically with the content of
your thoughts
so you're broken in Broad enough to feel
a bit
and then it continues to say and what is
the right uh sunkappa thought that is
Noble undefiled a factor of the path
it's the thinking the directing of the
Mind the contemplating the application
the verbal Sankara in one of noble mind
undefiled who possesses the Noble Path
and develops the Noble Path
and they make an effort to give up ranks
wrong thought and take on right thought
that's the right effort
and then mindfully through recollection
they give up on thought and take up
right or that's their right mindfulness
so these three things keep running and
soaking around right some cover what I
thought namely right few rights
yeah um in relation to this I find useful as
um in relation to this I find useful as
the phenomenon of um the movement and uh
yeah so like unwholesome
thoughts agitate
agitate
the mind yeah and
yeah absorb it in in movement uh whereas
wholesome thoughts
um still the mind yeah well it kind of
again comes down to that if you just
think about a phenologically about the
nature of a trap
like that there's always some some sweet
reward of some sort and you watch the
Nature Documentaries and you have those
closing flowers and stuff they track the
insects and you it's not even that hard
or much of a stretch to recognize oh
well human realm is not that different
it's always like this trap and then like
10 years later it's like just this
weight on you and you realize oh you're
imprisoned and you have been since that
day
um and and that's exactly that you
realize that if your own thoughts
pressure you and it's unpleasant and
offer your reward if you act out of it
that's a trap and as the suit is
described again you don't need to know
who's setting up say you walk in the
nature and you see a weird news
and you see a weird news
and then some loose leaves now would
would you like would you be able by any
stretch of your imagination to think
that somebody set it up for a good
purpose would that even occur to no and that's
would that even occur to no and that's
exactly what the student said a hunter
does not set up a trap wishing for
welfare so you recognize your own thoughts have
so you recognize your own thoughts have
a setup of a trap
it's like well that cannot be for my
welfare accepting that
and that's how far that principle goes
and that's that choice we spoke about
when you do have a choice to then yeah
but still
you're trapped to that extent and if
you're trapped in your thoughts you'll
be trapped in your speech you'll be
trapped in your body eventually and
thinking about it because it's like the
thing is you're already you start
trapped it kind of starts
it's as though
like you take this body as something
pleasant agreeable and and good
because you start as in this inter with
this intoxication of Youth intoxication
of Health you think that these things
are you take tend to take these things
for granted
and you know by virtue of how you happen
to now be young and healthy you can
access Pleasant sight sounds now state
touches um
um
but it's like you know you imagine if
somebody were to have kidnapped you and
beholding you hostage or something
um and they say you know any day that
they keep that you know it's not hidden
from you any day you know that they
might start torturing you or they're
gonna kill you and they tell you that
like there's no nobody is is happening
to other other prisoners
but you know for the time they're kind
of playing with you I'll like I'll give
you some video games to play I'll give
you some good foods and and you wouldn't
be you forget you forget that you're
actually hostage and but if you were to
actually stop taking these things
you know you could you could see that
there's you know a way out basically
that's the only way yeah yeah because
you don't start by being free yeah so
you have no reference point that you're
now a hostage you're already your
starting point is fully distracted
hostage fully distracted prisoner that's
the one that's the problem and the way
to become aware of the situation of the
prison is stop taking up distractions
intentionally and then you you would and
that's exactly why people fear that like
a Solitude bottom just boredom is
terrifying to people
like even you don't have to go to Great
Solitude and you know fearful places and
so on Wilderness just stop distracting
yourself and sit alone in your room and
you're gonna just board them will be
like because that already reveals well
because that already reveals well
the the outside situation yes at the
other end of this situation